foreign
we're here for another episode of the
usada pitch and I'm excited to be joined
today by Dr Laura Lewis he saw as
director of science Laura oversees our
athlete biological passport program and
she leads many of our sample collection
and Analysis Innovation projects today
she's going to tell us more about one of
those projects involving a new blood
collection device called the tasso plus
which actually made an appearance at the
recent Boston Marathon thanks for
joining me Laura
I agree
um I'm super excited to be talking to
you about the Tesla plus today as you
know I'm really passionate about all
things blood testing and the athlete
biological passport so any way that we
can make blood testing more efficient
and importantly athlete friendly is a
huge deal for me I've actually got a
device here if you want to have a look
yes please that would be great oh yes so
this does look a little
so DBS device so what's the difference
between that and the tasso plus you know
you're very observant totally right it
does look very similar because this
button here is the same technology as
the the standard DBS device but the main
difference is the tasso device draws
liquid blood so it's whole blood and
it's exactly the same as the blood
that's drawn from a standard
venipuncture but just without a needle
and this actually collects
six times less blood than a standard
dinner puncher and even better it's
virtually painless wow uh can we see it
in action yeah sure so all I need to do
while we well we're sitting here is I
just pop this on my arm up here
and press the button
and then as we continue talking
um you know this this is gonna collect
blood so we'll see how it goes okay and
you didn't even make a face when you
push the button
it doesn't matter just like a tiny
little prick that's awesome so tell me
what type of analysis is possible from
the tassel plus sample
yeah so as I said
um it collects liquid blood so the
possibilities for analysis are pretty
much the same uh that we would have from
a standard in a sample so at the moment
the tasso offers a gold top tube and a
purple top tube so the gold is used for
analysis for certain prohibited
substances like growth hormone or EPO
whereas the purple top tube is used for
the standard blood parameters of the
athlete biological passport I've started
bleeding oh it's happening yeah it's
happening
so what can you tell me about the trial
in Boston
uh we were really excited to partner
with the Athletics Integrity unit at the
Boston Marathon and we really wanted to
see how this device could perform in the
field so we knew from standard lab
trials that you know works really well
in that controlled laboratory setting
but if we want to implement it in the
future we have to see how it performs
you know in in the real world in the
competition
so we took the opportunity at Boston to
ask athletes who were selected for
testing if they would also agree to
provide a tasso sample and then we were
able to compare the results from the
tasso to the um their famous in the
sample that was collected of course it
was really important that this was The
Athlete's own choice and that
participation was voluntary but the
majority of athletes agreed which was
totally awesome
and the feedback was really positive
both from the dcos and the athletes and
so we really hope that the data from
this trial will be a significant step
forward towards implementation
that's awesome so how do you envision
the tassel plus being used in the future
well I would love to see a world where
athletes don't have to be subjected to
Venus blood draws or at least if we
could certainly significantly reduce the
number of blood draws so I really hope
that micro capillary devices like the
tassoplas could be
integrated into the anti-doping system
particularly in times when it's more
efficient or practical or better for The
Athlete's well-being so you know
certainly when it's a collection that's
quite close to competition
of course for that to happen there's
various validation and investigations
that need to need to happen but we're
really committed to this journey and you
know we're so grateful for all the
athletes out there that are assisting us
with this process
so can we see the device at this point
yeah sure so I've collected
um it's not quite finished collecting
its sample but we're almost there
um and it's you know just been
filling up slightly as we've been
talking
slowly and painlessly that's awesome
all right well thank you so much for the
great info Laura that will do it for
this episode of the usata pitch and we
will be back again soon
[Music]
thank you